a new infinite combo is getting a lot of
attention prior to a major Regional
Championship leading players to believe
they can simply draw out games and steal
a free win as well as raising the
question does a player have to pick a
detrimental choice in an infinite Loop
or not let's jump into it and find out
so the combo in question is the Amalia
wild growth Walker combo at dream hack
Atlanta on the final day the deck
accounted for nearly 15% of the meta
making it the most played deck of the
final day the combo is quite simple and
can go off as early as turn three wait a
second didn't we just have this problem
on turn one you cast lunar veteran on
turn two you cast Amalia gain a life
explore and on turn three you cast wild
growth Walker gain a life and
effectively go infinite you explore
again with Amalia which triggers wild
growth Walker which gains you a life
which triggers aalia and you repeat this
process until am Amalia hits 20 power at
which point she destroys all other
creatures and clears the way for a
likely lethal swing thanks to Amalia
destroying all other creatures she
breaks the loop by herself but what if
wild growth Walker was
indestructible the Amalia combo decks
are naturally playing protection spells
like tamio safekeeping to protect either
of their two main combo pieces but if
wild growth Walker is made to be
indestructible as aalia is comboing
before she hits 20 power the loop cannot
be broken unless the opponent is able to
remove Amalia from the board which means
the combo player can simply reveal a
non-land card on top of their library
and just perpetually leave it there gain
infinite life and draw out the
game or can they okay that's the last
time I'm doing that bit in Magic the
Gathering there's technically no such
thing as infinite and what we actually
need to know about is two different
types of loops loops caused by players
actions or lack thereof and Loops caused
by players choices let's take a look at
these two different examples let's say
we have an Emy lurker of the lock
Paradox engine and a MOX Amber in play
and we have another MOX Amber in the
graveyard we activate Emery to allow us
to cast MOX Amber from the graveyard we
cast it for zero Mana the Paradox engine
triggers allowing us to untap Emy MOX
Amber resolves the legendary rule kicks
in and we send one of the MOX ambers to
the graveyard and of course we can now
repeat this Loop
indefinitely the next example we need to
look at is this interesting interaction
between guko Relentless the double face
Plaines Walker and Spark double if we
have Gro Relentless in play clone it
with spark double and with the spark
double grouo and use his zeroc cost
Plaines Walker ability targeting a 2 two
wolf token the wolf would deal two
damage to spark double group with which
would trigger his flip ability however
single-face clones of transform cards
cannot transform so assuming no player
has any Plaines Walker removal or damage
spells this ability would trigger
perpetually now if we turn to section
4.4 of the magic the Gathering
tournament rules it tells us exactly how
to handle infinite Loops effectively for
any Loop both you and your opponent have
to choose a specific number of times
you'll go through through the loop at
which point the player who chose the
lowest number of iterations will receive
priority and get a chance to intervene
or in the Emory example the players
would agree on how many times the loop
is going to be performed and then
continue playing the game taking a
different action Loops where an
individual player actively takes actions
like optionally casting spells or
activating an ability to perpetuate the
loop cannot be used to draw out a game
in the guko spark double example however
players must choose a number of times
the loop will occur before they decide
to intervene and break the loop if both
players wish to take no actions or they
simply can't the game will end in a draw
this is because no player is maintaining
the loop no players are taking actions
to trigger the loop the game state is
triggering it by itself and the players
have no other choice now this brings us
back to the indestructible wild growth
Walker Amalia Loop let's say today we're
past the 20 power point and we've left a
nonland card on top of Our Deck can we
simply just leave it there constantly
reveal it and simply draw out the game
now first of all why would a player want
to do this well to simply draw out a
game and potentially run out the round
clock so they can win the round if
they've already won the first game
secondly because this is a trigger that
keeps on occurring choosing to Mill the
card would eventually leave the player
to reveal the whole deck to their
opponent and pass on otherwise hidden
information so what's the outcome here
it's important to understand a couple of
things here firstly in competitive magic
you often hear the words best of three
thrown about when talking about the
types of matches you'll play in in a
tournament this is technically incorrect
as it implies you'll be playing a
maximum of three games again if we turn
to the tournament rules we can look to
section 2.1 for the answer a magic match
consists of a series of games that are
played until one side has won a set
number of games usually two drawn games
do not count towards this goal if the
round ends before a player has won the
required number of games the winner of
the match is the player who's won the
most games at that point if both players
have equal game wins the match is a draw
so this means a player must win two
games in order to win a round you simply
can't win the first game and then draw
out the next two for a round win okay
okay so drawing a game isn't really
advantageous for the combo player here
the loop can be demonstrated and the
players can quickly move onto the next
game if they have no interaction so what
about that revealing SL Milling part
does the Amelia combo player need to
reveal their whole deck well if they're
attempting to draw out the game they do
but then this leaves them wide open for
a massive Counterattack one of the last
paragraphs of the tournament rules
section on Loops States this
Some Loops are sustained by choices
rather than actions in these cases the
above rules may be applied with the
player making a different Choice rather
than ceasing to take an action the game
moves to the point where the player
makes that choice if the choice involves
hidden information a judge may be needed
to determine whether any choice is
available that will not continue the
loop so all this means is that no a
player cannot just simply reveal the top
card of their deck over and over over
again to attempt to get a draw they have
to pick a certain number of times
they're going to do that and then choose
an alternative option which in this case
is putting the card into the graveyard
this Loop will repeat until the combo
player has no cards left in their deck
and here's the interesting part if
neither player has a way to interact
with this combo the game will end in a
draw but if the combo player's opponent
has a way to remove the Amalia they're
now facing down a player with an empty
Library who's going to lose the game on
their next draw step because they don't
have any cards left to draw so now you
know how to handle infinite Loops in
Magic the Gathering be sure to leave a
like if you learned something now if
you're fancy taking a deck like this for
a spin in Commander you should check out
bathroom Brew's abzan explore Commander
video so what do you think about this
combo is this another powerful Exelon
card that needs to be banned or do you
think this combo is a lot easier to stop
and interact with than the previous
combos we've seen thanks for watching
and I'll see you in the next
one